<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jean Arman Du Plessis, Duke of Richelieu, and peere of France: his life, &amp;c. / Set forth by Gabriel Dugres.</title>
            <author>Dugrès, Gabriel, fl. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81809</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867777</idno>
  <idno type="VID">120103</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240944826</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1174_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208858</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867777</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867777e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1174[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jean Arman Du Plessis, Duke of Richelieu, and peere of France: his life, &amp;c. / Set forth by Gabriel Dugres.</title>
                  <author>Dugrès, Gabriel, fl. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Fawcet, for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Richelieu, Armand Jean du Plessis, --  duc de, 1585-1642 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120103:1"/>
            <p>JEAN ARMAN DU PLESSIS, Duke of RICHELIEU, and PEERE of FRANCE: His <hi>LIFE,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Set forth By GABRIEL DVGRES.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by THO: FAWCET, for the Author. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:120103:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120103:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT, AND EXACT Narration of the most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable things, done and spoken by that Grand Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of <hi>France Iean Arman du Plessis, Cardinall</hi> of RICHELIEU.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Write here the Life of a Man, which hath been as much admired, envied, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and hated as one, that ever <hi>France</hi> brought forth. The best, and rarest wits admired the vast capacity of his transcendent mind. Some others, that aspired as high as he, but wanted his reach, envied him. They that could not endure the prosperity, greatnesse,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120103:3"/>and flourishing estate either of the King, or of the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> hated him, but they, that rejoyced at the King, or Kingdomes welfare, loved him. I feare, least as an unskilfull limner doth injury very much a handsome, and compleat face with the drawing of it: I likewise blemish the lustre of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that most eminent Polititian, and true Patriot, with my ruffe pen. I know, that it is with Polititians as with lovers: none can conceive, or expresse the passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a lover, but he that hath been in love himselfe. Neither can one imagine, apprehend, or lay open the subtilties, plots, inventions, and tricks of a Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, that never was employed in any State businesses. But on the other side, the greatest piece of policy being to hide it: I hope to be easily excused, if I doe take only upon me to write the most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>Cardinall</hi> his birth, life, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, without searching any further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wayes, then the outward deeds,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120103:3"/>and effects can afford us. It were a meet folly to undertake to set forth a thing, which he hath alwayes kept close, and private to himselfe. I take him to have farre exceeded <hi>Machiavel</hi> in his policy, who made the world acquainted with it. Many became good <hi>Theorists</hi> with reading his books, but few good practitioners. Policy once knowne is no more policy. They that follow the common road of it, shall be soone met withall. It is the head-piece that must be a true Polititians book. A quarter of an houre of our Red hats study hath many times overthrowne the designes, projected and concluded by a long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultation of the grave <hi>Spanish</hi> Councell.</p>
            <p>None can taxe me of adulation in writing the <hi>Cardinals</hi> life, hee being dead, and the King his good master like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise: and in a time, in which most of them, that were of his fide, are perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in <hi>France.</hi> I can hope for no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment by writing of it, but I will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120103:4"/>render testimony unto the truth as farre as I know it: and I will honour that brave mans memory; they that are well-wishers unto the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> shall build him a monument in their owne hearts. That those things I write of the <hi>Cardinall</hi> may find more credit with the reader: I will intreat him to know, that there are but few in <hi>England,</hi> that know, or can write more things of him according to the truth, than I can doe. I was borne but ten leagues from his owne native place: I lived at severall times in <hi>Lodun</hi> a place but 3 leagues distant from <hi>Richelieu.</hi> They that have knowne the <hi>Queen-Mothers</hi> Court in the beginning of the <hi>Cardinals</hi> rising, knew likewise <hi>Messieurs les Botrus</hi> born in the City of <hi>Angiers</hi> which got into the Queenes favour at the same time: did continue in it as long as the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall:</hi> were promoted to the Kings ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the time of the <hi>Cardinals</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion: and to the wonder of all men,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120103:4"/>carried their cups so even, that in the midst of all troubles, and of all the plots and conspiracies wrought by the Queens favorites, and others against the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> they were never found tardie, were maintained in their honours, and lived in favour with the King, and <hi>Cardinall</hi> both. I spare telling what relation I have to them: This onely I will say, that my Father was borne likewise in <hi>Angiers,</hi> and that his younger brother lived in the Kings Court with them. This will suffice to make the reader think that it is probable I may know sufficiently of the <hi>Cardinall</hi> to write his life. The occasions I had these late yeeres to be with some <hi>French</hi> Lords, which were even displeased at his favour, and government, made me know many things more at large: for, if any thing could have been spoken against the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall,</hi> it was not kept private in their houses. But, to speak true; I never heard the Lords themselves speak any evill
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120103:5"/>word of him, as they were men of great understanding, they did esteem highly of his rare parts. The <hi>Cardinall</hi> was borne in the yeere 1585 in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Castle of <hi>Richelieu</hi> three leagues distant from the city of <hi>Lodun,</hi> upon the borders of the Provinces of <hi>Poictou,</hi> and <hi>Tourraine.</hi> His Pedigree is derived from <hi>William du Plessis,</hi> who lived under the reigne of <hi>Phil. Aug. Anno</hi> CLXXIX, unto <hi>William</hi> succeeded <hi>Peter</hi> second of the name, <hi>William</hi> the third of the name, <hi>Peter</hi> the fourth, <hi>William</hi> the fifth, <hi>Peter</hi> the sixth, <hi>Savage</hi> the seventh, <hi>Francis</hi> first of the name, the 8. in whose time the house of <hi>Richelieu</hi> entred into that of <hi>Du plessis, Francis</hi> the second, the ninth, <hi>Francis</hi> the third, the tenth, <hi>Francis</hi> the fourth, the eleventh, Father to <hi>Iean Arman du Plessis Cardinall,</hi> Duke, and Peere of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. One of our Historians writeth that <hi>Francis Du Plessis,</hi> second of the name, was married unto <hi>Guyonne de la val,</hi> which was a kin
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120103:5"/>to the house of <hi>Bourlon.</hi> Our <hi>French</hi> History maketh mention of the valour, and of the warlike exploits of many of that house, and amongst all the rest, of <hi>William</hi> the first of it, who went into the Holy Land with <hi>Philip August.</hi> A house in <hi>Paris</hi> bearing the name of a family is none of the least marks of its antiquity, and noblenesse. Many <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> families enjoy the same honour in <hi>London.</hi> As <hi>Arundels</hi> House, <hi>Essex</hi> House, <hi>Suffolke</hi> House, <hi>Southampton</hi> House, <hi>Northampton</hi> House, &amp;c. <hi>L'hostel de Richelieu</hi> hath been very famous in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> these many yeetes; to the greater glory of the family of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> gave the name of it to one of the gates of the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> when he did enlarge a part of St. <hi>Honorius Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urb.</hi> The Palace called, <hi>Le Palais Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal,</hi> in St. <hi>Honorius</hi> Street, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called <hi>Richelieus</hi> Palace. Our <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> did put <hi>France</hi> into a maze in his youth. For, his quick, and subtile wit,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120103:6"/>his judgement ripe afore the wonted time, and the proofes hee gave of his rare parts in the Schooles of humane learning, shewing himselfe a most elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Rhetorician, and a subtile, and sound Philosopher made the world think that there was something in him, which did savour more of the Angelicall, than of the humane nature. All these things being done by him under the age of eighteen. Hee studyed Divinity in the famous, and ancient faculty of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> to the wonder of the most learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of it, which admired the solidity of his reasons, and the subtility of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which passed many times their solutions, and answers. He went out Doctor in that Colledge; <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonse</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Lucon</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave his Bishoprick over to him, and betooke himselfe to a <hi>Carthusian</hi> Cloister, <hi>Iean du Plessis</hi> being not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that charge by the Canons of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for want of age, <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:120103:6"/>the fift dispensed with him by reason of his deserts, and learning. Returned to <hi>Paris</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> he went to give hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thanks to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and to kisse his Majesties hand, who received him most favourably, and told him that this was the first dignity the Church had bestowed upon him; but his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits would obtaine the greatest shee could conferre upon him. They that have read our <hi>French</hi> History know of the conference held in <hi>Lodun</hi> 1616, where the greatest Princes, and Nobles met after the damnable murther, and ever bleeding death of the most renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and never to bee so gotten <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth: to consult about the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes affaires. The <hi>Cardinall</hi> got there acquaintance with the best and chiefest Courtiers. A very neere kinswoman of his being one of the <hi>Queen-Mothers</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Honour, commended him to her Mistresse, who after the knowledge of his extraordinary parts admitted him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120103:7"/>into her Court, and Councell. Some have thought it dishonourable to the <hi>Cardinall</hi> that a woman should bee the first that introducted him into the Queens Court. It is not so. Courtiers are all like those of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they need one Saint, or another to bring them into the presence, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their Soveraigne. If it be a he, or a she Saint, it mattereth not. <hi>Jean du Plessis</hi> Bishop of <hi>Lucon,</hi> was not long after nominated Embassadour in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary to the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to treat betweene him, and the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voye.</hi> But the Queene seeing that hee could doe better service at home, made him the Kings first Secretary. His fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility in the expedition of most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and difficult affayres, his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Counsels, his politenesse in his conversation, his eloquence in his discourses, his subtility in his replies, his Rhetorick, and elegancy in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and diligence in dispatching bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesses
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120103:7"/>made the world sufficiently know what hee was. The Marquesse of <hi>Ancre</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> borne, husband to the Queenes Foster sister, played his pranks in <hi>France</hi> about that time, and did do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineere over all the Princes, Nobles, and over all the whole Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi> Even so much that hee came to that height of pride, and scorne of the Councell of State, that hee was wonted to tell them that hee did not aske them counsell of what hee was to doe, but onely of what they called formes of proceeding. Hee became at last intollerable to the King himselfe, who commanded Mr. <hi>De Vitry</hi> Captain of his Guards to pistoll him, which hee did performe according to the charge he had. Here is a remarkable thing of our Bishop; that, although he was the first Secretary of State during the base government, or rather tiranny of the Marquesse, yet hee did carry himselfe so discreetly, and so wisely, that hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120103:8"/>kept the Kings favour still. <hi>Monsieur de Luynes</hi> his Majesties only Favorite, assured the King, that <hi>Messire Iean du Plessis</hi> Bishop of <hi>Lucon</hi> had served him well, even during the Marquesse of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor</hi> his time, who was pistolled, as wee have told. The Queen somewhat sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of his death retired her selfe to <hi>Blois.</hi> Our Bishop had leave given him to waite upon her thither. Hee stayed there not much above a moneth. For, his envious perswaded the King that hee was a bad Counsellour to Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty. Hee went thence to his Priorie of <hi>Caussay,</hi> where he made a booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Christian Doctrine;</hi> Envie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him so farre, and got him a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moove from thence to <hi>Avignon,</hi> in which <hi>Henry</hi> Lord of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> and <hi>Monsieur Du Pont</hi> his Brother in Law were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. His Brothers death was the the greatest unhappinesse hee had there. The Duke of <hi>Espernon</hi> did convey the <hi>Queen-Mother</hi> out of the Castle of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120103:8"/>
               <hi>Blois</hi> to <hi>Loches,</hi> and from thence to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goulesme.</hi> Many did say, and more did think that the Bishop of <hi>Lucon</hi> was the projector of that designe. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all this, the Duke of <hi>Luynes</hi> the Kings Grand Favorite sent him a letter to desire him to returne to the Queene: The King himselfe wrote with his owne hand these following words. I desire you to believe that the things above written are according to my will; and that you cannot please me better, than if you doe according to them. Some thought the reason, why the King sent for him back againe out of <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> was because hee feared least hee should passe over either into <hi>Savoye,</hi> or into <hi>Italy:</hi> for, he had sufficient proofes of his working braines; and some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did conceive, that the King being desirous to be reconciled with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thought no man so able, or fit to work his reconciliation as the Bishop was. Who, took his journey towards
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120103:9"/>the Queene presently after the receit of that letter: he was arrested betweene <hi>Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Vienna,</hi> by the Captaine of the Marquesse of <hi>Alincour</hi> his Guards, but soone after set at liberty by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse himselfe after a complementall excuse. The Queene having set her hand to the agreement betweene his Majesty and hers: sent the Bishop of <hi>Lucon</hi> with them to the King; They were both fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably received. The King told the Bishop, that he thought himselfe bound to acknowledge his good service. By that agreement the government of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers, Pont de ce,</hi> and <hi>Chinon,</hi> was given to the Queene. The King, and the Queene were not long after up in armes one against the other. <hi>Le Pont de cé</hi> stood against the King, some few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, and unwise men were killed of both sides. The King took <hi>Le Pont de cé,</hi> new agreements were drawne by his Councell, and sent to Her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty by <hi>Monsieur de Crequy;</hi> She signed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120103:9"/>them, and returned them to the King by the <hi>Cardinall de Sourdis,</hi> and the Bishop of <hi>Lucon.</hi> Many have thought that these bickerings between the King, and His Mother were but counterfeited, and that it was but a trick to raise men to fall upon the Protestants before they could make a considerable party to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the Kings forces. I cannot affirme it for truth. I will only say that the Warres against the reformed in <hi>France</hi> begun not long after. (Would to God the Kings, and the Parliaments forces would now joyne together to fall upon the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebells in case they could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together, and make a true, blessed, and happy Peace in <hi>England.</hi>) 1622 our Bishop of <hi>Lucon</hi> was made <hi>Cardinall</hi> of <hi>Richelieu.</hi> 1624 He was chosen to bee the first Minister of State, at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piegne.</hi> 1626 The <hi>Cardinall</hi> perswaded the King to make sure of the Duke of <hi>Vendosme,</hi> and of the <hi>Grand-prior</hi> his naturall brothers. To call the States
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120103:10"/>to <hi>Nauntes,</hi> where the Earle of <hi>Chalais</hi> master of the Kings Warderope was beheaded in the month of <hi>August</hi> in the same yeare. It hath been said openly enough in <hi>France</hi> that their plot was to put the King into a Cloister, that hee might apply himselfe the better to his devotions without any disturbance by the care of his Kingdome. And so <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> his brother was to be set in the Throne, and many of the Nobles were to share either the Kingdomes parts, or, the dignities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves. How true it is, I know not. But, if it was so, the <hi>Cardinall</hi> did the King no small ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the discoverie of the plot. Some thought otherwise of it: for it was said in <hi>France,</hi> that there was nothing inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded against the Kings person, but that all their aime was at the <hi>Cardinall</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: who was a great eye-sore unto them. He was in 1627 made Admirall of <hi>France;</hi> the Duke of <hi>Montmorency</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120103:10"/>his place unto him, for which the King gave him the government of <hi>Languedoc</hi> the Duke did not like of that exchange as it appeared afterwards. 1628 The <hi>Cardinall</hi> was made Generall of the Kings forces against that famous, and renowned City of <hi>Rochell;</hi> before which the King had spent five moneths already, and three Kings had besieged it afore him. He did more with his wit, and policy, than all the Kings forces could doe by their strength. For, he bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled the Sea; and to the wonder of all the world, built a banke to stop the passages of those Ships that would have been sent out of the City to fetch in reliefe: and to keep any other from sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into it. <hi>Rochell</hi> was at last forced to yeeld unto the King after a tedious famin, who entred into it on all-<hi>Holy-tide</hi> 1628. Thus a brave, and well fortified City, which stood afore against two, or, three Kings, and which was thought impregnable: was taken by the device,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120103:11"/>and subtility of the <hi>Cardinall.</hi> I will relate here some <hi>French</hi> verses made by some of the Kings forces, two, or three moneths afore the surrendring of it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parlez moy de la Rochelle</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A-ton rompu son canal.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cette ville Rebelle</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perdra le nom de pucelle</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Par l'espr it du Cardinal.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>He knew that it could not bee taken but by famine, he wrought all the means conducing to that effect. The victuals borrowed out of it for the <hi>English</hi> Navy a going into the Isle of <hi>Ré,</hi> was no small preparation unto it. For, they were never payd againe, as they say. I cannot think that the good Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> had so base a designe, as to be accessary to the ruine of such a place, and of men, that professed the Religion, he professed himselfe. But such was perhaps his bad fortune to be ill thought of by some of the <hi>English,</hi> and by all <hi>French</hi> Protestants. The twentieth of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120103:11"/>
               <hi>August</hi> 1629, the <hi>Cardinall</hi> entred into <hi>Montaulban,</hi> and was royally enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Citizens, which had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen him for their Governour. They used that honest policy, seeing that there was no possibility that they could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand alone, all the Kings army, and in a manner whole <hi>France</hi> it selfe. They had prepared a rich Canopy for his more honourable reception: he thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them saying, That it was fitter for a King than for him. Our <hi>Cardinall</hi> was chosen that same yeere Generall of the Kings forces in <hi>Piedmont.</hi> When he was at <hi>Suse,</hi> the <hi>Queen-Mother</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be jealous of his prosperous suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, and endeavoured to lay an asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion upon his fidelity: yet the King well perswaded of his Lovalty, gave no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to her words. She consulted with Mr. <hi>de Marillac</hi> then Lord-Keeper of the Great Seale in <hi>France,</hi> how she might rid her selfe of the <hi>Cardinall:</hi> but their consultation proved very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>successefull
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120103:12"/>to both: for, Mr. <hi>de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillac</hi> lost his bead-piece; and the Queen went to take the fresh ayre into <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xels.</hi> Yet notwithstanding all this: the <hi>Cardinall</hi> asked her before the King, if he had committed any thing against his Majesty: and she answered, no. Hee wrote her this Letter,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Know how my enemies, or rather the enemies of the State not contented to have discredited me unto your Majesty; endeavour besides to bring my abode neer the King, into suspition: as if I came on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neer him to remoove him from. You and to divide what God, and nature have joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I hope in the divine bounty that their malice will be knowne: that my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portments will hee shortly justified; and that my innocency shall triumph over ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie. It is not</hi> MADAM, <hi>but, that I count my selfe unfortunate in that I cease
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120103:12"/>from pleasing your Majesty: and, but life is odious to me in the state I am, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the honour of your favour, and of that esteeme, which I loved farre more than the greatnesse of the earth: as I hold it from your liberall hand, I doe likewise bring it, and prostrate it at your feet. Excuse</hi> MADAM <hi>your owne work, and your creature. All that shall proceed from your Royall humour, shall be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by me without murmuring, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with a thousand blessings. But</hi> MADAM, <hi>spare I beseech you (through that piety, which is naturall unto you) the purple of the Church wherewith you have cloathed me; which will loose its splendour and lustre, if your Majesty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printeth in it so black a spot. What like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-hood, that the most obliged man were the most ingratefull; and that my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, my interests, and my first incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation binding me to your service, I should have separated my selfe from it, through the onely advantage of gaining
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120103:13"/>unto my selfe the name of traytour unto my best, and greatest</hi> QUEEN <hi>of the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That well considered</hi> MADAM, <hi>should absolve me from crime, and from suspition before the Tribunall of your Majesty: which hath almost condemned me without bearing me. But I appeale not from it, because I am infinitely well resigned unto all your will, I subscribe unto my disaster, and I will not contend with my Soveraign Mistresse, nor aske her reason of what she hath done, neither doe I think to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my selfe with the support of my Master, nor with his Officers, nor with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my former services, against the course of your indignation: the very thoughts of it would be guilty; and farre from the inclination which I have alwayes showed in seeking for glory in Loyalty, and for security in the only innocency. I desire much lesse to draw a miserable fortune in</hi> France, <hi>or to carry it into</hi> Rome, <hi>to see therein more lamentable ruines than mine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120103:13"/>owne. It would be tedious unto me to be in any place from which your Majesty should be absent and without the leave to see you, I have none else but to dye. But, I could wish for my reputation sake, and for the ranke I have in the house of God, that it were after my innocency was knowne: and (if it is not too much audacity in me) after the recovery of your favour. If this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth unto me, I will grieve no more to depart from Court; nay, from the very world. I dye howsoever a thousand times a day, since your Majesty maketh as if you did believe that I am no more my selfe. That is to say,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>MADAM of your Majesty</salute>
                     <lb/>
                     <signed>The most humble, most faithfull,<lb/> and most obedient servant<lb/> ARMAN, <hi>Cardinall<lb/> de</hi> RICHILIEU.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:120103:14"/>
            <p> THe Princesse of <hi>Conty,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> the Dutchesse of <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Fargis,</hi> Mr. <hi>de Marillac</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed, and his brother, <hi>Monsieur de Belle-garde,</hi> Mr. <hi>de Bassompierre, &amp;</hi> Mr. <hi>Vautier</hi> the Queens Physitian have been thought to have all conspired together the <hi>Cardinals</hi> ruine. But, they could never undermine him; for hee was grounded upon the rock. As he was constant in his faithfull service to the King: so did his Majesty likewise never alter, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish his favour to him: but he did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encrease it from time to time, and so continued it to the <hi>Cardinals</hi> death and his not surviving long after him, might happily cause many one to think, that the griefe he tooke for the losse of so constant a Subject, did advance his dayes. 1632 the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> took up armes against his brother, and invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the broyles the ever-renowned Duke of <hi>Montmorency,</hi> but unfortunate, and overseene in this onely businesse:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120103:14"/>who being wounded and taken prisoner at <hi>Chastelnau, d'Array,</hi> by the Marshall of <hi>Schomberg</hi> then Generall of the Kings forces: was carried to <hi>Tolouse,</hi> where being only 34 yeeres old he lost his head upon a Scaffold. All the Court, nay whole <hi>France</hi> did grieve for the misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death of so compleat, and so Noble a Duke. And so much the more, because so ancient, and so faithfull a race to the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> did perish, and dye in him. He being the first man of his Progenie, that had ever committed any fault against any King of <hi>France,</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve pardon. <hi>France</hi> would have bin ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thankfull to the <hi>Cardinall</hi> for the procuring, and to the King for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. But, publike good cannot ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times consist with private good. It is often needfull that men of greatest births, and parts suffer punishment for their faults, to the example, and terrour of those that are either of an equall, or of an inferiour rank with them.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:120103:15"/>
            <p> I leave of here tracing the <hi>Cardinals</hi> life yeere after yeere, and writing of his dignities. For, I can say in few words, that ever from 1631 untill his death, he was the only man, upon whom the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed the trust of his whole Kingdom, and of the affaires out of the Kingdom: and who was the maine instrument of his Majesties will. Many indiscreet, and ignorant persons have wrongfully taxed our deceased King for want of wit, imagining themselves that the King did let the <hi>Cardinall</hi> rule, because hee himselfe was not able to governe. They wanted wit, and knowledge in their censure. The greatest part of a Princely wisdome being to chuse wise, understanding, and faithfull States-men: and to be able to discerne between them that are truly affected to the good of his Crowne: and them, that seek onely their owne ends, and which put him u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon designes, destructives to himselfe, and to his Kingdome. Judicious, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120103:15"/>wise men shall ever think, and beleeve, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth was of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, and rare judgement, and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Since, he was able to judge, and chuse among the rest, one that went farre beyond any man of our age, in wit, understanding, Judgement, and Loyalty to his King, and Kingdome. I will speak a bold word. The antiquity had never any that exceeded him: few, or none, that could be paralleld with him. Many have been grand Polititians, as <hi>Elius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janus,</hi> and such like: enjoyed great dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and were in great favour with their Soveraigns. Fortune did smile u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them for a while: she raised, and extolled them to the height of favour, and then she brought them to the lowest of the disgrace, and dishonour. Most of them dyed an unnaturall death either by poyson, by the sword, or by the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. It is thought that Mr. <hi>de Luynes</hi> the <hi>Cardinals</hi> predecessour was poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It is knowne in <hi>England,</hi> that the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120103:16"/>Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was stabbed with a knife by <hi>Felton.</hi> I have seen my selfe my Lord <hi>Wentworth</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Ireland</hi> to loose his head upon a Scaffold on <hi>Tower</hi> hill 1641. So miserable is the condition of most Favorites. For, some things they undertake, prove well to their advantage, and glory: and some others very ill, and disadvantageous both to them, and to their Kings. But the <hi>Cardinall</hi> was ever fortunate from the first minute of his favour to the last moment of his life. The Kings favour did continue, or rather increase to his very death. Let envie it selfe speake, or name that one thing, hee undertooke, that ever proved to his shame, to the disadvantage either of his King, or of his Kingdome. His enemies gave bad constructions to his designes: but the events of them shewed him faithfull to the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> When was the name of the <hi>French</hi> more glorious, than in his time? When did any King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120103:16"/>get more victories, and conquered more places in so short a time, than <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth did through his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels? I doe not say that the King took the <hi>Cardinals</hi> counsell without using his owne discretion: but, that knowing him the wisest, and most faithfull of all his Counsellours, he gave more credit to his counsell than to any bodies else. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one have thought that the <hi>Cardinall</hi> did rather work by the Kings direction, than the King by his counsels; and that the King had given over to him the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of his affaires upon a meer po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy. So did a gentleman of great rank, and one of the middle Temple tell me: who having occasion to speak with his Majesty, was entertained by him with as much courtesie as any one could be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained: The <hi>Cardinall</hi> came then to the King, which commended the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to him. His <hi>Eminency</hi> gave him but a nod; but the businesse was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to the gentlemans ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120103:17"/>We are often deceived, when wee thinke that Favorites work all of themselves. They are but instruments of their Masters will. If the things they doe, be pleasing to the people, they have their good words, if displeasing, all the venome, and anger is vomited against the poore favorites. The King is safe from their hatred. They say, that he is the best natured Prince, and the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonnaire King, if it were not for his base, and wicked favorite. It is so many times, I confesse it: but yet; favorites are too often thought to bee the givers of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, and contrivers of designes, when they are but the executors of them. Kings, and other Soveraignes conceive many times great matters, and frame grand designes within themselves: They lye in their heads, untill they be fit, and ready to bee brought forth: The favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite must doe the office of a Midwife to give them entrance into the world. For, Princes are like <hi>Jove,</hi> their bearing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120103:17"/>place is the head. It is seldome seene that a favorite endeavoureth to crosse the disposition, or to alter the naturall inclination of his Master: he doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther observe it, and sympathize with it as much as hee can. <hi>Cicero</hi> giveth the character of an observing favorite in these words. <hi>Loquitur ad voluntatem, assentatur, assidet, admiratur.</hi> So that: if the Princes nature is good, hee dareth not counsell him any bad thing: if bad, he seldome goeth about to amend it. A good nature may (I deny it not) be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by bad counsels, and more especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they doe appeare in the shape of good. An easie, and a debonnaire one may easily. bee wrought upon. Evill words corrupt good manners. Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many lies, because they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented unto them cloathed like truths: and they doe often commit evill, when their Councell perswadeth them that they doe good.</p>
            <p>Let us speak now of some of the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:120103:18"/>rarest parts, and that <hi>pro modulo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro,</hi> according to our possibility: For, to undertake to comprehend them all, were to doe as if one did goe about to put all the water of the <hi>Thames</hi> in a Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle-shell. To presume to describe them fully, and as they were. It would be as if a picture-drawer would presume to animate his draughts: or rather as if he should thinke that the picture he hath drawne were equall with the live body. when it is but a meer shadow of it: so likewise, whatsoever (not I only) but also any man else can say of the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> brave parts, it will bee but an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect draught of his excellent perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>Every action of his life speaketh him wise: nay, his whole life (since hee had the use of reason) was but a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued wisdome. <hi>Rome,</hi> which was in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages the dwelling place of wise men, and the sea it selfe of wisdome, and is now (to give every man their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120103:18"/>due) the rendez-vouz and receptacle of many wise, and excellent wits: did take him for a young <hi>Apollo</hi> when hee went thither to be made Bishop by <hi>Gregory</hi> the 15. For: every sentence hee spoke was an oracle. Hee made the depth of his wisdome knowne unto the said <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> but under the secret of confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the Pope said then that hee would overturn the whole world. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered some yeeres after, the face of the affaires of <hi>France:</hi> and almost of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wisdome of a man is knowne in his words, and in his deeds: wee shall speak of his deeds, when wee come to discourse of his policie. As for his words, we will relate some of his wise sayings: but wee will leave of many, because they might perhaps distaste some that should read them.</p>
            <p>The old Latin Proverb saith, that, <hi>Vir sapit qui paeuca loquitur.</hi> A man is wise that sayeth but little. Wee have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120103:19"/>likewise two old Proverbs in <hi>French</hi> to this purpose. <hi>Parlez peu; parlez bien. Parlez rien, ou parlez bien.</hi> The first is in <hi>English.</hi> Speak little, speak well: and the second is: speak nothing, or speak well: If every man did observe that rule punctually, and followed those Proverbs exactly, it was the <hi>Cardinall.</hi> For, except in publike meetings, and when State-businesses were in agitation, he spoke very little, or nothing at all: we said afore, that when the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe did speak to him in the behalfe of an <hi>English</hi> Gentleman, hee nodded only unto the Gentleman and gave him never a word.</p>
            <p>The Poet said, that <hi>Semel in anno ridet Apollo.</hi> Our <hi>French Apollo</hi> did hardly laugh once in two yeeres in the sense that the Poet speaketh it. Hee was not of a frowning Countenance, though he was grave: his gravity was not severe, but accompanied many times with smiles.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:120103:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Here follow some of his Sentences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is only for great minds to goe on in their designes though their actions be censured, and controlled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The best book of a States-man, is Experience: that only book will make him sooner, and more learned, than all the Politicks in the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The borders of Kings Empires are measured by their strength. I doe not like of this sentence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Private faults in States-men, may be pardoned, but they, by which the publick is offended, can, and must never be excused.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To neglect the punishment of great crimes is still to permit, and to give an encouragement for the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of greater.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To punish men of a low conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and let the great ones be unpunished, is to kill little Snakes, and to let great Dragons live.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That businesses or imployments make man.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:120103:20"/> 8. He said that he approved not of that saying of <hi>Tacitus. Fortunae saevienti submittendus animus.</hi> The heart must yeeld unto the cruelty of fortune. But said, on the contrary, that the more fierce, and cruell fortune is, the greater must a wise mans courage be, and the more stiffely hee must stand against her. Hee hath put that saying of his, in practise during many yeeres; for, the greater was the rage of his great enemies, the more constant he was in his wayes: and went on the more couragiously in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes he had projected for the good of the King, and of the Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That a States-man must seek for glory in his fidelity, and for security in his innocency.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That absence is the best safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for one that hath offended his Prince.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That men must not be rash, and precipitated in their counsels; when the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120103:20"/>matter concerneth the good of the Prince, and of the Kingdome: but, when the resolution is taken upon a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, to be slow in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is to shew a kind of unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and to incurre the danger of sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That it is a generous kind of vengeance, to let our enemies know that we can avenge our selves of the injuries they have done us, and yet, pardon them.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That the Favorites center must be the good of his King, and of his Kingdomes: all his designes must be as the lines drawne from it, which must end into it.</p>
            <p n="14">14. He said that although the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, favour, and greatnesse of accusers useth to cast men accused into despaire: yet a faithfull States-man must bee the more resolute, the greater his accusers are, and the more constant in his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: because it will adde to his glory (when hee hath cleered himselfe) that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120103:21"/>he hath withstood the false accusations of so potent enemies.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That a States-man that desert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the service of his King, and Kingdom by reason of the many oppositions, and difficulties hee meeteth in his way: is no better then a traytour, that betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his King, and his Kingdome: and giveth them both in prey to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the greatest strength of a King, and of a Kingdome consisteth in reputation. For, if their enemies thinke them strong and couragious, they dare not make any attempt against them: and their neighbours will seek to have a league with them. If they goe about Conquering, or about regaining any thing, that was formerly lost: Their very name, and fame shall conquer, and regaine it.</p>
            <p n="17">17. When some of his Friends did tell him, that he had many enemies, and that hee was in great danger of his life.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120103:21"/>He answered thus. <hi>Satis est si hoc ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus ne quis nobis malè facere possit.</hi> It is enough (said he) if we have where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to keep any body from offending us. If hee meaned by these words his guards, or the Kings favour I know not; perhaps he meaned them both.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That we must never hazard with losse, that, which wee can obtaine with security.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That one, that is in favour can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not free himselfe from envy, but by loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, or leaving that favour, which is the cause of envie.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That a man, that endeavoureth to mend those things, that are corrupted in the States, shall never want dangers: because the remedy must bee violent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst corruption: and violence is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That a Prince desirous to govern his States with justice and to keep the love of his Subjects, ought not to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish by force that which he may obtain
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120103:22"/>by faire meanes, neither to aske by arms what is due unto reason.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That people feele more the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time, than they feare the time to come: and that they complaine for a small matter that they contribute for their defence, and preservation: and thinke not that their totall ruine is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by that meanes. That they know not how to chuse the lesser evill: as an (expert Pilot doth) which seeing his ship tossed by the winds, and in danger of a ship-wrack, casteth into the Sea a part of his fraught to save the rest, and thinketh not to loose what hee giveth willingly for the preservation of his life.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinall</hi> used these words to shew, that it was lawfull for him to leavie mony of the people for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of his necessary warres.</p>
            <p n="23">23 That he approved not of the <hi>Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> opinion, which is, that faith must not be kept with hereticks. For, said he, if wee ought not to keep it, wee ought
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120103:22"/>much lesse to give it them.</p>
            <p n="24">24. When some of the Protestants back-friends told him that it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have but one Religion in <hi>France:</hi> because the diversity of Religion is apt to cause dissentions, he answered them in these words. <hi>Maneat concordia bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolentiae inter sententiâ discordes.</hi> Let them that differ in opinion, agree in mutuall love.</p>
            <p n="25">25. That publick services must bee rewarded by publick charges, and not with money; because the recompence must be knowne for the encouragement of others: and must last long, that it may be remembred the longer.</p>
            <p n="26">26. That it is better to prevent crimes, than to punish them: and that it is to doe a favour unto them, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to doe evill, to take away from them the power of doing it.</p>
            <p n="27">27. That patience must atchieve, what strength cannot end.</p>
            <p n="28">28 That the Science of vanquishing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120103:23"/>consisteth in making good use of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
            <p n="29">29. That precepts of Policie may be easily put in writing, but hardly in practise.</p>
            <p n="30">30. That men attribute many times to a deficiencie of wisdome, that, which is a meer want of fortune.</p>
            <p n="31">31. That it is better to confute, and convince our accusers, and enviers by our vertues, and good deeds, than by words of purgation.</p>
            <p n="32">32. That a man, that thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe learned and wise enough, is an <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus,</hi> and a foole. And therefore though he was so litterate, and so under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing a man, he did neglect no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of benefiting himselfe either in learning, or in wisdom. To that effect he conversed with learned men as much as his grand imployments could permit him. Nay, hee stole many houres from his naturall rest to heare severall books of learning, and especially of ancient
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120103:23"/>histories read unto him by some young, and learned Student. Mr. <hi>Bodin</hi> a young <hi>Sorbonist,</hi> now beneficiate in <hi>Paris</hi> was one of the last. The grave <hi>L'Escot,</hi> now Bishop of <hi>Chartres</hi> did wish him, and commend him unto the <hi>Cardinall,</hi> which did benefit himselfe mightily by hearing those books read unto him: For; then he framed, and builded his designes upon the actions of the ancient, not that hee imitated, or followed them strictly, for he went farre beyond them; but because, that lecture did help somewhat his mind, and memory after a painefull day of serious imployments.</p>
            <p n="33">33. That, as the diversity of voices maketh a perfect harmony, provided that there be a discordant concordancy: so likewise in a Kingdome, or in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publike: The disparity of persons, of offices, and of dignities, maketh a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect consort in case there bee an union, and an agreement amongst them. There must bee a Prince, and Subjects, great
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120103:24"/>ones and little ones, a Magistrare and a people, some to command, and some to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. If they keep all time, and be not out of tune, the melody will be very sweet.</p>
            <p>I conclude the discourse of his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by that which <hi>Balzac</hi> said of him (though too prophanely by his leave.) That he was so wise, that God might repose the government of the whole world upon him.</p>
            <p>Let us now speak of his Policy, which is very neere a kinne to wisdome. We cannot judge of any mans policy but by the effects: Though wee doe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute many times unto policy those things, which are but meere fortune: and on the contrary, wee censure mens wisdome, when wee see some events which doe rather proceed from the want of fortune, then from the defect of prudence.</p>
            <p>It is much to conceive, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject grand designes: but it is more to bring them forth, and to execute them.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:120103:24"/>
            <p> The life is in the action. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth one to aime at brave ends, if he cannot tell how to find out the meanes to execute them?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinals</hi> chiefest end was to make the King of <hi>France</hi> absolute, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and renowned: and his Kingdome to flourish. To obtaine it, he removed all the obstacles either at home, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that could be any hinderance to his proceedings. Hee did imagine that so long as the Protestants had strong Holds, and pledge-townes in <hi>France,</hi> the King was not absolute in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and therefore hee did put the King upon the Protestant warres, and perswaded him to take all the places they had, from them, it was done so. The King got the masterie. His policy was like to prove disadvantageous unto the King, and to himselfe afterwards. For, except the Protestants had been in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of helping them; his mast er, and hee, would have been in great danger.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120103:25"/>1632, His wisdom could not but dictate him that the strength of the Protestant party in <hi>France</hi> is the preservative of the Crowne, and Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi> But, what he did then, he did it out of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that he might be called no more the <hi>Cardinall Huguenot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were many great men, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in <hi>France</hi> like to stirre, and to side with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> he caused some of them to be imprisoned, and some others to bee put to death: happy were they, that could escape the bad day, and get over out of the Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee knew that the house of <hi>Austria</hi> was a great annoyance unto the house of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> and that it kept too much light from it. Therefore he endeavoured to pull it downe piece by piece. 1631, He called the King of <hi>Swedeland</hi> into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> to give the first stroake; he did like a very good workman, and had not death prevented his designes, that house would have been levelled with the ground a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120103:25"/>now. Generall <hi>Bannire</hi> did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the work pretty well, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> are a working still. The <hi>Catalonians</hi> and the <hi>Portingals</hi> have had each one a very good pull at it, they were all the <hi>Cardinals</hi> workmen, he was the Grand Enginiere. They that he thought to be inclined towards the house of <hi>Austria,</hi> and which he perceived to bee more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firous of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> prosperity, than of the <hi>French</hi> were prevented in their designes by some businesses hee gave them at home. I could enlarge my selfe upon this subject. I could shew the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, and reasons, which moved him to doe so. I could name some persons he imployed in that businesse. I could tell how hee dispersed, and broke the <hi>Spanish</hi> faction in a Kingdome, that shall bee namelesse. I rather grieve to think of the miseries, in which they are now than doe desire to relate the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and occasions of them. And if the <hi>Cardinall</hi> were now alive, I beleeve that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120103:26"/>he would rather seek to compose their distractions, than to further them: for, he would be contented to see the <hi>Spanish</hi> faction disinabled for helping the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard.</hi> And perhaps they, that are now Counsellours of that Kingdome would rather side with <hi>France,</hi> than with <hi>Spain:</hi> or at least they would deale equally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt both: for, when we deale betwixt two of our friends that are at oddes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves: we shall make one of them our enemy, if hee perceiveth that we rather take part with his enemy than with him. The Pensionaries, and Intelligencers he kept abroad, cost him fifteen thousand crownes a week. Mr. <hi>Delope</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> or a <hi>Portingall</hi> was the man, that payed most of them.</p>
            <p>There could hardly bee six men in a company but three of them were of the <hi>Cardinals</hi> spies, or Intelligencers; and many times the whole company proved all intelligencers. And yet they knew not one another, and every one of them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120103:26"/>endeavoured to intrap the others. It was likewise so with his pensionaries: for: though hee had many in the same place, and in one Kingdome, yet hee would not have them know one another. He had two men, unto which he gave the charge of all the affaires. One was to take care of those that were within the Kingdome: and the other did onely look after forraine businesses. He im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted his designes unto them telling them, that none but they knew them, and therefore if they should ever be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, they were to look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Mr. <hi>de Chavigny,</hi> and Mr. <hi>de Noyers</hi> were the men. <hi>Cardinall Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> his successour, and during his life his collegue, and another himselfe: did concurre much with him for the good of <hi>France:</hi> for he was of one mind, and of one heart with him.</p>
            <p>One thing I dislike much in his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. It was his way of getting, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Souldiers: For, when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120103:27"/>unto the King his Master his great designes for advancing his glory, and for the destruction of <hi>Spaine:</hi> the King asked him how he should get soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers enough to bring these Grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes to execution. Being, that none are pressed in <hi>France,</hi> and that none can be forced, or compelled, except Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, which are called the <hi>Arriere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban:</hi> and are onely to attend his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties person upon extraordinary, and most important affaires. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth that invincible Monarch of ours, called them, and they were prepared: but <hi>Ravaillac</hi> munster of nature, and the shame of <hi>France</hi> did cut off his designes by stabbing of him. <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth of late, and happy memory called them likewise when he went into <hi>Italy.</hi> The <hi>Cardinal</hi> intreated the King to take no care, and to let him alone for that: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause hee had a way to get his Majesty more souldiers than be should need. To that effect, he laid many heavy taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120103:27"/>upon the people, and so: the poore he made more, the more souldiers hee got. Hee knew that the breaking of trades-men was the making of souldiers. The best piece of his policie was to make no use of those Grand Polititians, Grand Contrivers, Grand Plotters, Grand Disturbers of the Peace of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> which men call <hi>Iesuites:</hi> First, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he knew that they were too well affected unto the Crowne of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to prove faithfull unto <hi>France:</hi> Secondly, by reason that they think to have ingros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed all the wit, and policie in the world, and so would have every body to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or governed by their Counsels, which ever proved destructives. The old Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> did undoe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and all his Empire by believing of them. It is very strange that those Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niscient Gentlemen knew not the way to <hi>Pamprou.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinall</hi> imployed much one Father <hi>Ioseph</hi> a <hi>Capucin</hi> Fryar, who
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120103:28"/>though he wore a very course garment had a very refined wit. Hee did <hi>France</hi> great service; especially in <hi>Germany:</hi> and it is thought that the <hi>Cardinall</hi> was ruled by his counsells whilst hee lived. Their enimies did set up one night at the <hi>Pasquill</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> these lines against them both: nay, against the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the King of <hi>France</hi> himselfe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Papa <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ster inurbanus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rex par<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Christian<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cardinalis infernalis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>S c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>qualis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reple<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>undum totis malis.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>This I will say for his reaching poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and no more. That his mind was like a circle, which can containe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther figure, but cannot be contained by any. So likewise: he could comprehend all <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> policie, and devices of any <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but none was able to apprehend, or to conceive his own wisdom, and policy. <hi>La V<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, La S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se, Casal, L<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rraine, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> St. <hi>Honor<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Et</hi> St. <hi>Marguerite</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:120103:28"/>Islands, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rin, Tort<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, Pignerol, Arras,</hi> Aire, (though lost again) <hi>Cata<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingal, Perpignan,</hi> &amp; <hi>E.</hi> have selt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his policy. He had alwaies an equall mind in prosperity, and in adversity, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding not in one, &amp; being not desicient in the other. As he was nor transported with over-joy, so likewise he was never cast down, nor dejected by griefe: using a moderation in his prosperity, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in his adversity; which was not because he had ever any bad successe in any of his enterprises: but, by reason that he had so many enemies, which did seek his life, and the mine of <hi>France.</hi> Though he was constant, he was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensible: his heart was not made of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond, neither was it like <hi>Piadarus Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noas</hi> his skin, which was so tuffe, and so hard, that he did dart back the arrowes that were shot against him. He was no Stoick, but his constancy was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a reasonable wisdom: for hee did grieve sometimes when there
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120103:29"/>was occasion of grieving, and he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: but yet, was no wise distempered, for, he had so great a command over his passions, that they were all at his beck, they obeyed his call: they went no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then reason could afford them to goe: for she was alwayes their guide, and leader.</p>
            <p>Once onely the <hi>Cardinall</hi> broke out into passion, when the newes of <hi>Walstein's</hi> death was brought to him: for, then he did bite, and tare his hand karchief in pieces, and retired himselfe into his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set for a while. <hi>Walstein</hi> was (as almost every body knoweth) the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> his Generall. The <hi>Cardinals</hi> designe was (as men did conceive) to make <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> himselfe King, or at least <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> and <hi>Walstein,</hi> which was to give his souldiers unto the King of <hi>France:</hi> was promised the Dukedome of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> But, the designe being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, <hi>Gourden</hi> Governour of <hi>Egger</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:120103:29"/>killed <hi>Walstein February</hi> the twenty sift, 1634. and foure of his Captaines, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Page, when they were all at dinner, and then cryed <hi>Vive l'Empereur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was so excellent a Rhetorician, that if truth it selfe, and all the Orators in the world had been of one side, and he of an other: yet he was able to make his opinion to be thought, and received for the best. Therefore, we must not wonder if he did ever draw men unto his side, and if his Counsels were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved with a generall applause, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with a generall consent: Since his mouth was the Organe of Truth it selfe (I mean in civill affaires) and that he never used his Rhetorick, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare truth unto men, and to make them believe, and follow it.</p>
            <p>The assembly of the most noted, and chiefe Gentlemen of <hi>France,</hi> held in <hi>Paris</hi> about the latter end of 1626. heard many pieces of his eloquence. He perswaded them all to yeeld unto
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120103:30"/>the Kings demands as being just, and to consent unto the Articles His Majesty did propound them. The second of which was that the Protestants in <hi>France</hi> should be maintained in their ancient freedome, priviledges, and liberties.</p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Chalais,</hi> which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, or rather miserably butchered in in <hi>Nauntes,</hi> hearing that <hi>Madamoiselle de Montpensier</hi> was promised unto <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> the Duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi> Broke into these words. Thou hast a perswading <hi>Demon</hi> O <hi>Cardinall.</hi> The Marshall of <hi>Schomberg</hi> used to tell him, that they did deferre, and yeelded much unto him: not so much because of the authority, in which the King had placed him, as for the strength of his reasons, and of his eloquence.</p>
            <p>He stole every bodies heart through the eares, his speech was so charming that he enchanted every one. None did ever part from him unsatisfied. For he knew how to winne mens love, by a wise,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120103:30"/>and discreet complacencie: for though hee was somewhat stately, hee was not scornefull; and though hee was of a pleasing humour, he was no flatterer. Yet many have said that they were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly deceived by him, and that he was like a <hi>Camaeleon</hi> that assumeth all kinds of colours, except the white: but, it was black envie that made them speak so basely against his free, and sincere candour. For, as he never bestowed any praise upon unworthy Subjects; so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, he never dispraised deserving men. Deserts were alwayes rewarded, and faults punished by him, using a discreet wisdom both in his rewards, and in his punishments. Hee discerned betweene false, and true parts of men. He never took temerity for a great spirit, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse for good husbandry Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for courage, prating for eloquence, stupidity for modesty, Insolencie for freedome, and in a word: he never mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stook vice for Vertue, or Vertue for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:120103:31"/>vice; nor Truth for a lye. For, the light of his understanding dissipating the clouds which kept things hidden from other men, made them to appeare unto him as they were: so that he esteemed of every thing and of every one as he was indeed, and not as he was in other mens opinion: or in his owne. He ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured much the Nobility of Bloud, but he did respect farre more the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Vertue. And indeed; since all bloud is of a colour, and since it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther health, or sicknesse, that maketh a difference in mens bloud, I see no reason why we should worship, and honour so much men onely because they are No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly descended: and why we should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect so little Vertuous, and brave minds lodged in bodies of a meane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction. I grant, and will give the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due unto Noble-men for their rankes sake: but I shall never Idolize a thing, that commeth by meer fortune. I will admire a Vertuous, and a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120103:31"/>soule in a Noble mans body as a rich Diamond set in gold: but I will esteem no lesse of a like Diamond, if it were set in brasse. I say that it is much to be borne Great, but it is more to become such by Vertue, and merits. The envie, which the Princes, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men of <hi>France</hi> borne unto the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> because he did not let them have, and share all the offices, and dignities of <hi>France,</hi> hath occasioned me to fall into this discourse. For, they thought that great charges were intailed upon onely Great, and Noble-Houses. But the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> was of another opinion. If Vertue, Deserts, and Nobility met all in one Subject, that party was sure to be the object of his favours. The Earle of <hi>Arcour,</hi> the Marquesse of <hi>Alincour,</hi> The Marshall <hi>de la Mesteraie,</hi> and the Marshall of <hi>Breze</hi> being all of Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, have been honoured by him with many brave charges, and dignities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he knew them vertuous, and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120103:32"/>And be sides them, many others, which I name not, for, it is not my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to make here a catalogue of them upon which hee bestoved the favours due unto their merits, and noble births. Amongst all, which were not of so Great; and of so Noble Houses, yet ascended almost to the highest dignities of <hi>France,</hi> I will name only the ever renowned <hi>Gassion,</hi> that brave, undaunted, and conragious spirit, the terrour of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the glory of <hi>Bearne,</hi> and of all <hi>France</hi> it selfe, who was imployed as a Generall by the <hi>Cardinall,</hi> and even after the <hi>Cardinals</hi> death had the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shals</hi> staffe sent to him by the young King of <hi>France</hi> for a reward of his former services, and more especially for the great overthrow hee gave unto the <hi>Spanish</hi> Army about <hi>Rawcroy;</hi> where the most Noble, and most va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Prince (though yet very young in yeeres, the Duke of <hi>Auguien</hi> was Generall. <hi>Gassion</hi> was like another
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120103:32"/>
               <hi>Marius,</hi> amongst the <hi>Romanes;</hi> who being but meanly borne, ascended by his vertue to such a point of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that hee was seven times <hi>Consul,</hi> and preserved the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the powerfull enemies, which assailed it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinals</hi> favour, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse occasioned many Great, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men to make Factions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracies against the King, and the Kingdome, and against the <hi>Cardinall</hi> himselfe: nay (if they are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved) they aymed onely at him, and he was the sole object of their envie, they would free (as they said) the King, and the Kingdome from a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: for, they imagined that he ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized the Kings will, and that hee oppressed the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Wee have spoken of the plot about putting the King into a Cloister 1626, we have said enough of the insurrection in <hi>Languedoc</hi> made by the Duke of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120103:33"/>
               <hi>Orleans</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Montmoren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> 1632: we have said nothing as yet of that Grand Designe of the Duke of <hi>Beüillon,</hi> and of the Earle of <hi>Soissons,</hi> which get into <hi>France</hi> ayded with many <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and gave a great defeat unto the Kings Army: and had not the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals</hi> care, vigilancie, and wisdome stopped their proceedings, <hi>France</hi> was like to become a prey unto the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi> There hath been another plot of a newer stamp 1642, It was about bringing in tenne thousand <hi>Spaniards</hi> through <hi>Sedan</hi> to relieve the distressed, and oppressed <hi>French-men,</hi> and chiefly the Nobility of <hi>France,</hi> which was kept under by the <hi>Cardinall. Monsion do</hi> St. <hi>Marc,</hi> otherwise called <hi>Monsieur le Grand</hi> by reason of his dignity: was the chiefe contriver of it. <hi>Monsieur d<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fentrailles</hi> carried the Articles of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and s<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brought them signed by his Catholick<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Majesties hand unto <hi>Monsieur</hi> the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120103:33"/>Duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi> The <hi>Cardinall</hi> disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the plot: <hi>Monsieur do</hi> St. <hi>Marc</hi> was beheaded: and Mr. <hi>de</hi> Thou like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise: because the tender affection he bore unto <hi>Monsieur de</hi> St. <hi>Marc,</hi> as being his intimate friend, made him to keep secret a traiterous designe, from which he had discounselled the said Mr. St. <hi>Marc.</hi> but to conceale treason, is to be accessary unto it. The rest of the plot got out of the Kingdome. I have seen, and conversed with two of the chiefest for the space of foure, or five moneths together.</p>
            <p>Such kinds of plots, and conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies did concerne the generality of <hi>France,</hi> though their pretence was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to wit, the putting downe of the <hi>Cardinall,</hi> and the destroying of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended tyrannicall government. Let us now relate some Conspiracies which were intended directly against the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals</hi> person. One <hi>Alfeston</hi> borne in <hi>Chaalens</hi> was sent with two more from
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120103:34"/>
               <hi>Bruxelles</hi> be the perswasion of Father <hi>Chanteloube</hi> one of the <hi>Queen Mothers</hi> Councell; to kill him.</p>
            <p>The plot being discovered <hi>Alfeston</hi> was broken upon the wheele by the sentence given against him in <hi>Metz.</hi> One <hi>Chavag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac</hi> was convicted for having attempted to poyson his Eminencie with a letter. One <hi>Bernard</hi> a Physitian condemned for coyning of mony, confessed that he had promised to poyson the <hi>Cardinall. Adrian Bouchard</hi> a <hi>Romish</hi> Priest, and <hi>Nicholas Gargan</hi> noted Magicians (as they say) were hired to doe the like. But they had a rope for their hire the nineteenth of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1634 in <hi>Paris.</hi> Their books were burned, and the cinders throwne into the ayre. It was said that a great <hi>French</hi> Duke did crosse the Sea 1641, because two men disguised in Hermits habits had conspired his death through his perswasion. But I heard them, that were the chiefest in his house, affirme the contrary. After so many
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120103:34"/>conspiracies against him, after the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of so many strong enemies: to have him die a naturall death crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with glory, and honour: as much in favour with his King, as any man could be: it seemeth to me somewhat like a miracle. The King visited him in his sicknesse: which was the greatest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that he could receive of any mortall man: seeing, that, having lived altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his King, he was to die neere him, and almost in his armes, as if God had so disposed of his life; that being ordained for the service of <hi>Lewis</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and for the good of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: almost the very last breath should be spent in his Majesties sight. He desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his sicknesse, that he might live no longer, than he was able to doe the King, and the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> service. Had heaven been pleased to hearken to his prayers: and to geant him his request: his life would have been of an equall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting with the fates of the Kingdome of <hi>Prance.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:120103:35"/>
            <p> He expired on a Thursday being the fourth of <hi>December, stilo navo,</hi> and the 14. <hi>stilo veteri,</hi> 1642. being about 58 yeeres old. Hee left nothing wanting unto the prosperity of the King, and of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> but his owne person. Yet, the losse of so brave a man is in some measure recompenced by <hi>Cardinall Mazarin,</hi> who was the most intimate friend the <hi>Cardinall Richelieu</hi> had during his life, and one that knew the best part of his designes, and wanteth no wit to bring them to execution: and besides all this, hath given sufficient proofes of the zeale, and inclination hee hath for the good of <hi>France.</hi> So that <hi>French-men</hi> will never think that <hi>Richelieu</hi> is dead so long as <hi>Mazarin</hi> is alive. For, <hi>Richelieu's Genius</hi> remaineth still with <hi>Mazarin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinall Richelieu</hi> was buried in the Colledge of <hi>Sorbenne,</hi> where he had caused his monument to be built, during his life. There could not be a fitter place to receive the body in which so wise, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120103:35"/>so learned a soule did inhabite: than that brave, and famous house of Learning.</p>
            <p>Now: if you aske me of what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Cardinall</hi> was, you shall pose me. The <hi>Romans</hi> say, that he was of their Religion: like enough so, for he caused warres to bee made against the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants: he hath written a book called the <hi>Christian Doctrine,</hi> for the instruction of the <hi>Romish</hi> Priests: and some things of controversie against the Protestants; Which for all that think that he was of their Religion: he was called the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Huguenot</hi> for a great while: he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Protestants very much: and counselled the King even soone after the taking of <hi>Rochell,</hi> to protest publickly in the assembly of the most noted men in <hi>France,</hi> that hee would maintaine the Protestants in their Priviledges, and liberties. But, for my owne part, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that his religion, was best knowne unto himselfe; and, that it was as hard to dive into it, as into his policie. It is a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120103:36"/>common thing to say, that Polititians grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Religion, is to have none. Yet, it is not impossible to bee religiously poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. We may serve God, and our country likewise. I wish that <hi>France</hi> may never beare a worse Patriot than he was. That the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> may alwayes have as trusty, and as faithfull subjects. That the Reformed in <hi>France</hi> may never have a worse enemy; (all things rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered.)</p>
            <p>It is seldome seen that the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Clergy-men proveth so successe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto their Kings, and Kingdomes; as that of <hi>Cardinall Richelieu</hi> did. For; they doe seek oftentimes too much to exalt themselves, and their tribe: and by those meanes overthrow themselves, their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and the Kingdomes, or repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, wherein they live. For: the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great pride, and state of the Clergy is apt to breed a kind of heart-burning amongst the Nobility and Gentry: nay amongst some of their owne profession, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120103:36"/>the Commonalty. So that: they conspire many times altogether the ruine, and the down-fall of the pride of such men: which should rather gaine love, and respect by their humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation: then cause envie by their vain, and stately pompe. If the Clergy mount up their Canons against the Laiety: They will plant their Ordnance against them. If <hi>Justinian</hi> striveth to get the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand: <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror will so justle with him, that he will goe neer to thrust him out. Therefore, it is best for him to bee contented with the honour, and place, which is allowed, and assigned unto him: and not to desire to ascend any higher. Some say, that the <hi>Cardinall</hi> called the now Bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> his Ape. I cannot believe that his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency was so uncivill, as to speak so irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently of his Grace. Peradventure he called him his Imitator: and I would he had imitated him indeed. Kingdomes are compared unto ships, their Kings to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120103:37"/>Pilots. States-men, upon which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the government of the ship, may be called their Deputy Pilots, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Masters mates. The <hi>Cardinall</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned <hi>France</hi> intrusted to him, in all tempests risen against it without either shipwrack or losse: left it enjoying a good calme in the Haven. May it please God to let no tempest arise after the death of the Masters mate, and of the Master himselfe, that cast that brave ship of <hi>France</hi> upon some rock, or bank. A <hi>French man</hi> made two verses in <hi>Latin,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> by a kind of a propheticall spirit of the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a ship, and of the <hi>Cardinall</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pilot of it, I will end with them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Te duce sulcabit fluctus, portum{que} tenebit:</l>
               <l>Anchora nulla fuit divitiore loco.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Va navire ne craint point, ton Pilote est un Dieu,</l>
               <l>Jamais Anchre ne fut en un plus <hi>Richelieu</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>